ACTWU's Cotton Garment Control Department Records 5619/042
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU's Cotton Garment Control Department Records
1955-1978
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union.
Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America.
5619/042
2 cubic feet
2 linear feet
Correspondence, reports, publications.
This collection consists of Union Label agreements and correspondence with various manufacturers, mostly from Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, but a few from Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union.
6826817
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
may 19, 2010
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, July 2010
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related collections: 5619: Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America 5619/042 MB: ACTWU's Cotton Garment Control Department Memorabilia And all other 5619 collections.
Textile industry--New York (State)--New York; Textile workers--Labor unions--New York (State)--New York; Clothing trade--New York (State)--New York; Clothing workers--Labor unions--New York (State)--New York; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union --Archives; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America --Archives; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union --Archives; Union of Needeltrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE) --Archives; UNITE HERE (Organization) --Archives
6826817
- Appollo Shirt, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Union Label Agreement and Correspondence.
- Asbury Sportswear, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Ascot Manufacturing, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Ashley Shirt, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- William Atkin Shirt, 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Atlantic Shirt, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Banner Shirt, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bartlay, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Union Label Correspondence.
- Bayard Shirt, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Best Shirt, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Boblen Shirt (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Brill Shirt and Neckwear, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Burton Manufacturing, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Burnley Shirt, 1960-1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Butler Shirt, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Carlton Shirt, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Cluett, Peabody and Company, 1955-1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Creighton Shirt (Box 1, Folder 18)
- S. Dennis, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Die and Stamp Makers, 1955-1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Charles Dobbs, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Eagle Shirtmakers, 1955-1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Elizabeth Shirt, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Elm City Shirt (Box 1, Folder 24)
- El Rey Manufacturing, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Larry R. Engelson, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Enro Shirt, 1955-1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Fair Manufacturing (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Fashion Glenshire, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- M. Fine and Sons Manufacturing, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Flair-Tex, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Flushing Shirt, 1955-1976 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Fredwin Casuals, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Freedman Rodelheim Shirtmakers, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Fruitland Manufacturing (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Gant of New Haven, 1955-1975 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Gateway Manufacturing, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Glaser Enterprises, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Gold Medal Shirt (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Greystone Shirt, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Hamilton Shirt, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Harwood Manufacturing, 1955-1975 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- C. F. Hathaway, 1955-1969 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Hema Shirt, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Henry Charles, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Holbrooke Shirt, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Ide Shirt, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- International Ticket, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Joel Isaacs Shirt, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- F. Jacobson and Sons, 1955-1970 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- J. and R. Shirt, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Kaymore Shirt, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- David Kurtz, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Lehman Baer, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Lesnow Manufacturing, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Leventhal Brothers, 1956-1977 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Lido Shirt, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Linwood Shirt, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Loeb and Loeb, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Loev Brothers, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Lustbery, Nast and Company, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Lynn Shirt, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- McGregor Sportswear (D. Doniger), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Manhattan Shirt, 1955-1974 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Marlboro Shirt, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Marvlee Manufacturing, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Mather Shirts, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Steve Matson Products, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- M and B Sportswear, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Elton Meltzer, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Meyersdale Shirt, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Morgan Shirt, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- M and S Shirt, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Normandie Press, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Oberman and Company, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- O. K. Uniform, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Par-Ex Shirt (Sero of New Haven), 1956 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Park Guild Shirt, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Parkley Shirt, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Peerless Robes and Sportswear (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Pelham Sportswear, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Al Peter Shirt (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Pine Shirt and Pajama, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Pottstown Shirt, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Publix Shirt, 1955-1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Quaker Shirt, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- M. H. Raab Meyerhoff, 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Radiant Shirt, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Rich Guild Shirt, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Rivoli Shirt, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Rob Roy, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Rubury Shirt, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Sagamore Shirt, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Sam-Son Shirt, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Savada Brothers, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Seaford Garment, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Shelby Shirt, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Shirtcraft, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Shirt Label Requests, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Shirt Union Label Records. M, 1955-1972 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Form I, Form II, and Label Die invoices.
- Shirt Union Label Records. N-P, 1955-1977 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Shirt Union Label Records. Q-Z, 1955-1970 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Silver Springs Sportswear, 1956-1972 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Southeastern Shirt, 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Spaide Shirt, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- S and S Shirt, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Sportsville Menswear, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Stratford Shirt, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Robert Terry Garment, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Tyson Shirt, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Louis R. Ulanoff, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Neckwear Union Label Die, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Union Label, 1955-1970 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Union Shirt, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Usona Shirt, 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Victory Shirt, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Bernard Walsh (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Warrenshire Shirt, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Watson Shirt, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Weiss Shirt, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Whitney Shirt, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Wide Awake Shirt, 1956-1976 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- J. E. Wiegard, 1957-1965 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Wilson Brothers, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Yardleigh Sportswear, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 61)